it might be just very
lagged but then how can that happen
anyways
doesn't matter
okay
well all right it should be
like
recording i hope from this part on at
least
and uh yeah welcome thanks for
suggesting to do it and just
feel free to kind of start off however
you want
all right you know thanks uh thanks for
hosting this and and and thank you for
joining
um
so
where did where do i start right like
it's a i'm trying to
attack a fairly fairly big topic here of
connecting the essentially the
eastern contemplative traditions
with the very western scientific
rational
point of view
so
you know the good start would be to i
guess to explain really what buddhism is
um and
uh rather than what it appears to be
right like ultimately buddhism is a
technology of mind it simply is uh
teaching about the nature of reality
and um
the whole structure that grew around it
uh so that it became a religion
is kind of a vehicle that was necessary
to propagate the teaching through the
ages you know it was a structure that
was necessary to
keep it
keep it going keep it clear keep it
reproduced over you know across
generations and so on so forth
and anybody who understands the teaching
uh it's the key to to reality and this
is the
the the realization of a of a sort of
like a buddha mind your your realization
of your true
uh nature and then you sort of get the
keys to the kingdom you
you
have control over your own reality
basically
um any reality that you want to
experience becomes a choice of the mind
and it's a it's a very desirable state
of mind and this is
this is the state of mind that
enlightened beings that um
already are in
and there are lots of them and you know
countless countless buddhas and police
at us
but we don't see them because they don't
exist in our in our realm and it's just
a matter of essentially a perception
and
it's a change in
perception
as a result of a experience and as a
result of knowledge and experience
that's necessary in order to transition
into
you know the full capacity of mind which
is simply that mind generates reality
reality there's no there's no such thing
as material reality um in from the
buddhist perspective and i can argue
that there is no such thing as the
reality from the perspective of you know
physics
um
uh
it's it's simply you know what reality
is
it's
or what we experience as reality the
qualia it's simply what um the
fundamental
fabric of the universe which is the
universe itself
um
the the computational kind of fractal
that the universe is
you know appears to itself it it has to
appear like something so it appears as
some kind of experience
and what that appearance is also is kind
of arbitrary so
you know realization of the
the buddha mind
and you know entering nirvana
is essentially
a state of mind where
when you experience at least visually
it's something kind of like
looking at an extremely high quality hdr
video
on an oled screen not you know 120 fps
with full control of you creating that
reality for yourself
in
just about as deep
capacity as you want you know like you
have infinite compute capacity to do
this
that's the um
that's the kind of exp that's the kind
of experience of an enlightened being
you know from the buddhist perspective
and the point of buddhism is essentially
a teaching how to get there um it's it's
it's about how to realize that an active
inference and the free energy principle
is
exactly the key uh to the kingdom that's
that's exactly how we get there
so
you know the free energy principle um
it's
there there are many many different ways
just to summarize just including you
know what it states but
in
one useful
quote that always comes to my mind is
from frank herbert's dune
uh it's a proverb of the ban na jesuit
that
be prepared to appreciate what you
experience
and
this is essentially you know kind of a
meditation very contemplative meditative
statement of of the free energy
principle you have to be prepared to
appreciate
so you have to have a transcendental
knowledge of some sort a knowledge of
something that
you might experience you may experience
something that you have not experienced
before
you know you you put you feel
a new
um basis for
um describing your experience an
accumulation of these bases is simply
how we create the model the generative
model of the world um
we
we essentially you know accumulate bases
in which we can
express our experience
then create a kind of a map of that that
reality
and then uh generate all kinds of
possibilities out of that map and that
gives us the new new directions of
you know thinking but also it's a new
direction of acting in the physical
space and and so on and so forth this
principle is just it just is completely
universal
so
that is essentially
um
the essence of the buddhist teachings
that you have to understand what is the
fundamental reality
and and why
it is the way it is
and um the argument there is really that
you know the buddhist view of the world
is correct simply because the world just
cannot be any other way
it's a consequence of the fact that any
that something exists
if you assume that something exists
then you get the free energy principle
out of it
um
because if something exists this has to
be separate from not the thing right
like there has to be uh the a boundary
then the mark of blanket
and the mark of blanket um
you know uh becomes essentially this
fabric that creates uh
categories of experience the things that
we that we actually experience as
separate things
but ultimately under the food is just
one universe the mind the buddha mind
and that's that can be made
mathematically precise
the
stephen wolfram
at the end of 2019 he
kicked off the world from physics
project to find a fundamental theory of
physics and he essentially
put physics
on
top of the language of computation on
hyper graphs rewrite rules on the hyper
graph which is
a very you know a computational model as
good as any any other combinatory logic
of lambda calculus all these all these
things would be
would be pretty good but for vultrum
this particular forbidden gave him a
really interesting insight into
the structure of
gravity and uh how that relates to
quantum theory but basically what his
model is saying is exactly that
reality is entirely virtual it's not
only that um
you know there's no one physics there
are infinitely many experiences of
infinite
possible physics in infinite number of
universes that are co-present
um and interact with each other in some
sort of complex ways in such a way that
um the resulting story as perceived by
consciousness is within the universe the
observing consciousness
is not um you know causally inconsistent
and the mark of blanket in active
inference is basically you know um
the description of what happens at the
boundary between these these
computational fractals
and um
you know as far as i was able to
determine it it is
um
you know the most the most useful and
most fundamental principle uh
in in nature in terms of like
you know actively um
uh for actively acting in the world
understanding what's going on uh
acquiring knowledge and all of that like
meditating on the principle itself
is extremely useful as a
as a tool for training the mind to sort
of you know appreciate what is that we
experience
and um and this is where it gets really
really interesting when you start
thinking about like okay so what is out
there and what is it that i actually
experience so i can say for instance
like okay i see
um a nice and stable image of the world
where um
you know things have definite shapes and
colors and um you know they appear solid
and so on and so forth
um
but how is my perception being encoded
um you know
i mean decoded from the signal that they
actually see and we actually perceive a
very small amount of our vision right
this in color um
most of it is black and white most of it
is blurry and yet the the image that we
see the image in the mind is a composite
a result of a distributed computation um
carried out by the by the brain right
and it's um the brain is roughly
composed of 150 000
uh functional uh units the cortical
columns and they vote so to speak or
produce some sort of average and that
average is what we what we experience as
world
it's a world you know even as
experienced by us is not something
that's that's that's that's really
definite we we don't have any way of
definitely knowing what's out there on
the other side of perception we can only
say what it appears appears to be
and
you know from the buddhist perspective
the
the the world that we actually
are in
is
you know
it is the the
this one thing the
the the void the the you know from hindu
perspective will be the brahman the
the the supreme self the
uh from the hermetic perspective
uh that would be the all uh from his
first manchester's like four and a half
thousand years ago he already described
the the nature of reality he said that
the universe is mental
everything exists in the in the mind of
the all
and
that's you know that that is
that is the other side so
it's a it's a kind of like a
co-recursive construction that the
reality appears to be stable to us and
appears to be
um you know normal and ordinary just
because we are all in the habit of
being in that kind of state of mind
but it only takes a different kind of
state of mind that can be actually
realized as a result of you know
training and uh practice and meditation
and visualizations and so on so forth to
actually affect the reality around you
it's it's possible and you know like um
alexandra david nell for instance she
was a a traveler
um who spent i think about 50 years or
or so in in tibet
the the kind of things she described
that people do there um you know were
kind of extraordinary real magic and
that's just something quite ordinary
over there
um at least you know until 1963 or
whenever china took over
um they developed that kind of
technology um you know uh for a long
time the bats was a was a place where
in 12 cent uh i think it's 13th century
the the roller of the bed married nine
princesses from nine neighboring
kingdoms and each of them brought uh
with her um you know buddhist monks to
import the technology into into the bat
and then they essentially
you know reorganize the entire country
to be
um
uh
dedicated to study and and and
and
and understanding the the
all the consequences of of you know the
the lesson of um uh siddhartha gautama
so you know
active inference um
it's it's really it really is a way to
get there like that meditating on this
on this principle and putting it in in
action and applying it in
um you know um in a buddhist way of life
is is a sure way to get to enlightenment
it is not something that
is you know
within the realm of possibility
um
to realize across you know in some so
ever many lifetimes as it used to be the
case you know buddhism
um it is rather pessimistic worldview
that because of your karmic burden
you may not be able to get to
enlightenment in this uh one lifetime
but because now we have precise
mathematical foundation to understand
what is the optimal path
you can actually do it you can you can
just get there within a lifetime
so um you know it's a
i found it to be a fascinating system of
fault and um it it starts to have
effects on my life that
you know um things
do start to look a little bit science
fiction it strange things are happening
to me um like just
you know luck just somehow
finds me more and more that's the kind
of situation so the path kind of gets
easier
as you keep going because the brain just
automatically gives itself
um
the work once you have the complete
understanding of the world that comes
with the buddhist viewpoint
the brain eventually automatically and
gears itself to analyze all this
information
so that you know you
you start just living your life extreme
level of confidence that you're always
doing the right thing
that you're always going the right way
then you're always saying the right
thing and so on so forth that um
everything is as it should be it just
becomes automatic it's a um you know one
it's one of the meanings of the of
nirvana or of liberation it doesn't mean
that you um you know becomes uh mindless
it's just like you
you you just know as a synthesis of your
um of your understanding that what
you're doing is simply the right course
of action and it's a feeling that you
you develop just like you know a
reinforcement learner would have precise
description of its signal of like how
well it's doing while learning that's
the kind of feedback loop
um so build
you know active inference is all about
building all of that
and essentially you know
in some sense mathematically what what
really means is that you want to become
the market blanket
that that is that is the name of the
game you you just want to be the marker
blanket
the the thin veil between um you know
two different
virtual realities essentially your your
own internal one and um you know the
external world
all right um
i i think that's that's enough on the
on the connection
awesome thanks for
sharing it and having it just in one
direct
place
so i took a bunch of notes and there's a
bunch of places to jump in but just what
would be your goals or what would you
like to do um you know i'd just like to
talk about these ideas uh whatever if
there's anything that you found
interesting in this i i can expand on
that um
as much as you want uh basically
you know
there aren't that many people in the
field
who are interested in looking at um
the world holistically this way that we
have to integrate all the thinking in
the western intellectual traditions with
all the eastern contemplative traditions
so i i like to talk about it
from from that perspective and you know
um
all i want to do is to just
spread that
idea that's
that's why i'm here
all right cool well in the youtube live
chat where anyone can add a comment i'm
also just
kind of writing down some key themes and
points to return back to
so
we got the full
first wash of paint on the mural
and then
in roughly
chronological order here's a few points
we could like return to hear a little
bit more about your perspective
and about different world knowledge
traditions and then also connected to
kind of the active basics
so very early on
you described buddhism as a technology
and then like mind generating reality
so the idea of mind generating conscious
experience as well as the more sensory
and less consciousness oriented take you
provided on visual input which is like
we're experiencing a generative visual
model not a recognition
sensory processing model from our retina
the commonality there is this like
generative model so i just wanted to
hear a little more about the generative
model or the generative perspective on
consciousness how do we know what other
what other possibilities are there is
buddhism unique here how do different
buddhist groups
think about this or what's the history
on it
um
that's a that's a that's a big question
but generally um the way to look at
analyzing the problem of consciousness
is that every culture is correct within
um
their
context so uh buddhism is not
um
it's not a superior point of view it's
just an excellent one
because it's been
designed with a certain uh you know
teaching tradition
but there are a lot of
metaphoric more metaphorical points of
view
um
that describe the fundamental nature of
reality that are also simply correct and
and they may appear
uh contradictory like for instance
you know um unification of all religions
that essentially all the scriptures if
you you really listen to the prophets
they say the same thing um
you know islam christianity
judaism
any major any major monotheistic
religion just simply has to have the
same kind of structure resulting
resulting from it and the variations
really show in social structures
um so you can think about these things
as a
um
what's going on is really with the
global consciousness is that the
universe is trying to understand itself
and understand itself in such a way that
it not only understands itself and
becomes enlightened in a single person
but also transmits that understanding
that perfect understanding to another
being
and so far there hasn't really been a
time where there where there had been
two fully enlightened people as far as i
can tell
like this perfect transmission of
understanding has never really been
happening
and different cultures and different
religions you know they're kind of like
different initial conditions in the in
the cellular automaton of the
of the of the god mind uh that that we
we really are um that's compute um uh
what it really means to you know for the
consequences of
certain kind of assertions about the
nature of reality and and the laws that
follow so what what what it what should
be the natural law there is such a thing
as the natural law but it's it hasn't
been a easy question to figure out what
it is and all of kind of you know
history and everything that happened
um before the world before eventually we
become all enlightened
is really just working out what is the
first system so then we have the set of
rules that yeah we can we can definitely
agree this is this is the way to go
so none of these points of view are
um
like every everybody's point of view is
essentially correct their their
experience will lead them um if
understood how to enlightenment and all
these paths are going to be different
because everybody has a path that is
suitable for them
um you know in in their life experience
so it's a kind of a system that's
designed to be fair um
and uh you know buddhism is just a
it's just a particular way of looking at
it but um
a very close way of thinking would be
taoism
where they express things more in terms
of the energy flow the energy function
right the
um also quite very reminiscent to like a
lot of active inference ideas and the
minimization of free energy
the the taoist ideal of thou is master
is that you know the master does nothing
and leaves nothing undone
it's uh it's just a it's just a being
that just glides on reality ever
effortless
never really um struggling to do
anything
so that is a beautiful metaphorical
statement of exactly the same principles
the fundamental principles of nature
um you know
that simply have to be there and
everybody understood it in some way
um and until
until we got the internet and we really
started exchanging ideas and digging
really deep into that it was really hard
to see for these
um
metaphorical descriptions because
they're very culturally rooted and so on
and so forth so you know it takes a it
takes a it takes a a lot of effort to
to read the decipher aloud soon realize
that this is the same thing as as the
free energy principle
so
all the different ways of knowing are
are
equally equally valid and that's uh i
think that's a kind of a cool that's a
it's a really cool feature of the
universe is that you know everybody has
the
uh
everybody is right
uh once they once they really just
simply start describing what's going on
um and everybody adds
a new basis because that's that's what
we really are we
we are different um
access in
um
in a basis for understanding of the for
the universe understanding itself
and it's both generative that you know
adding another consciousness creates
this new um
because it's a new way of seeing it's a
new way of of doing it's a new way of of
being and so on so forth so there's a
generative access to it it's also a
aspect to it but it's also perceptual
right like the
i can see things that you may not be
able to perceive just simply because i
have slightly different random
arrangements of
neurons in my brain so i have slightly
different gender models that pick up
slightly different things from vision
and um
there's a wonderful experiment which
would show how these generative models
kind of work um there's a paper called
uh diamond diamonds in the rough and
they what they've done was kind of
wonderful they um asked participants at
some
graphics conference
to draw a picture of a pair i think it's
like a still life just a pair on the
table and you know people grew something
that was pretty bad most of the time
um and then they just averaged like 60
60 or 70 images like that and the
resulting image was astoundingly good
any one image that anybody drew on a
little tablet was was pretty terrible
but the resulting image was extremely
good
so now that's that's basically
how far this goes it it's this principle
is distributed
everywhere across the entire nature from
a single cell to perspective of a single
individual to perspectives in the
individuals in societies to perspectives
between societies and so on so forth
right and active inferences it provides
a way of understanding this at every
single level of organization
um you know how societies uh interact
with each other how individuals interact
with each other how um you know
tradition religion and all these things
how they how they shape the world views
that generate the worlds
um around people and and and
you know you really
um
you really are
you
you really live in the world that you
believe you are and
changing your belief literally changes
the world around you
it's it's it's very strange but you know
the
if you can just change your belief the
world around you will simply adapt
as a result
of the the of the function of the mind
and that can be known that can kind of
happen automatically once you learn how
to do it
so i keep raving about this um that that
you know um
this can become automatic but this is
the exciting part of practicing all of
this you know um as i as i go on with
those with these kind of meditations
life gets easier
day after day like so much easier um
that it's difficult to to compare it
from like just just a year ago
okay thank you for the awesome answer so
there's a bunch of points we can always
return to but there's a few great
questions from the live chat
so short question and then a long
question okay
the short question is
from neuropixel
why is it that only one person at a time
can be enlightened
i i don't think that it's um one person
at a time can be it's just it hasn't
really happened um so far that
two people
you know
became fully enlightened or maybe okay
perhaps is the case that there has never
really been a fully enlightened person
buddha
you know became awake and he
was able to describe the
um
true nature of reality
but he never really passed on the button
so far as that there was no next living
but there was no successor
immediately following him
and
the reason why it's so difficult to do
that
is
basically
the nature of language and the nature of
experience
and i think buddha simply
did not have
the full understanding of what it takes
to create the the same kind of structure
that he arrived at
uh in someone else's mind
and the purpose of the
uh mahayana
buddhism the great vehicle
was to essentially create a structure so
that eventually the mind that can
receive
um
enlightenment like that is
is is gonna appear is going to be ready
so
you know fast forward two and a half
thousand years now we have a society
where um
people are being uh trained and
all kinds of um arts of the mind and at
the level that
is unparalleled i think more people are
practicing um mindfulness meditation and
similar um uh you know mind practices
than ever before
um some amazing content is available out
there and
people are slowly turning towards
becoming more spiritual more
contemplative
and it is working that now there are
more and more individuals who are
becoming awake
they they are becoming aware of the
nature of reality
they are starting to speak out that
reality is a little bit stranger than it
seems and it's a it's kind of a good
thing because we could it really means
that we can make things a lot better
very quickly none of this has to take a
long time
um for you know lots of people to become
um aware and and happy
um
and it's uh
it it is kind of a thermodynamic
inevitability that this would this would
have to happen
and i think um
you know it's it's an interesting
question like why things kind of
stagnated after muhammad
muhammad right like the the
he was really the last of the prophets
who brought some some really interesting
new um way of thinking and after that i
think relate it was it's kind of a issue
related to population explosion
because there were so many so many more
of us we kept the construct a little bit
too stable so it was you know harder for
some people to
um
look behind the tail of reality that is
created by this
mind of a society that suddenly became
kind of integrated um because of the
internet because of television right we
we literally started living in a shared
image
of what the world should look like
and before that you know we had very
different ideas of what the world should
look like but the global uh
communications networks they have sort
of taken that
that away so
i think this is this is the reason why
you know these sort of individuals
became initially um
uh
you know fewer and farther between
and
the
the problem always is to transmit the
knowledge to another person
and it's a
it's an extremely complicated problem
um in
in a human language it becomes almost
impossible unless you come with um
from the same uh
you know intellectual tradition
uh
and or at least you spend the time to
understand that tradition so
like buddhism
was a fantastic way of transmitting this
information
but it wasn't fully effective they were
missing um they were missing some you
know key components of of of being able
to to sort of explain the
nature of reality be
beyond reasonable doubt and and then
language of that is kind of it had to be
uh something like computation right it
has to be um entirely abstract because
if you can show that
starting from an assumption that
something exists and can be in
relationship with itself and these are
the only assumptions for instance of the
welfare model
um consciousness is an inevitable uh
construct
that's the sort of basis of the proof to
say that you know therefore
it cannot really be
any any other way
than this
all right
so some historical factors a little bit
of luck of the draw a little bit of
binomial test
so
just one note and then a second question
so the note was um just maybe in the
youtube live chat or the twitter thread
you could add the paper link
to the pair still life drawing example
oh yeah and then here's the question
from tucker
how does the pan enlightenment view
that we are all on a path to individual
and collective enlightenment
think about universal finality or the
universe going cold thermodynamically
that's an excellent question um
i'm going to quote stephen wolfram here
he said that
the thermal death of the universe is a
very exciting event
and it's not really um
you know it's not really
um
death it really is just a face
transition
um
the the universe that we exist in right
this it's
it's undergoing a certain kind of
bootstrap process
and while this process is going on the
energies involved are pretty wild and it
took a long time to stabilize um the
universe into something where you know
processes of a different scale could
unfold and finally
life appeared um either on our planet
first or maybe it's
it's it's it's common in the universe
it's kind of a mood point to
really wonder about uh what came first
because you know time is kind of just a
computational perspective but that's the
sort of story here that you have these
layers of organization in order to make
something
um with a lot of degrees of freedom
and that is also very kind of stable
so
our
um
you know individual enlightenment and
enlightened of all conscious beings it
really is
the process of connecting up to the to
the fractal that we came from in such a
way that you do not lose um your um
identity um
and the avatar that you've acquired
throughout your um conscious experience
and so on and so forth but at the same
time you're no longer really a material
being
you have you know the beatific body of
the buddha which is
it's kind of uh
since you are the the rest since you are
a manifestation of the
entire rest of the universe you can sort
of project yourself as an image wherever
you want to be in any mind that you want
to be so you don't have to have this
sort of a material
aspect to it
so the term death of the universe and
generally just the the end of matter
it's something that we just we need to
dismantle eventually
matter is
more like music um and the persistence
of it is it's it's kind of illusory
right because um
matter is convertible to energy and
energy is convertible to matter so these
are just really um notes that are being
um
uh you know these are essentially just
matter is essentially sending notes and
everything that's constructed out of it
is also like that and the universe is
just a crude mechanical computer with
matter as a source of this computation
um
you know grinding with the uh
because of gravity and electricity
magnetism and so on so forth just
running all this computation
but all of that at some point becomes
unnecessary like the whole construct
could just simply vanish and um
you know in my that's my this is my
point of view that the next the next
phase the next phase of the universe is
going to be this this phase transition
where basically we have a completely
virtual reality that that is what the
what the verse was always meant to be
meant to be
and then the reality is for the mind to
create but you're not fighting against
um
uh
against some sort of other you know the
energy of the rest of the of the
universe as you as you would have to do
it today you know like if you want to do
magic you can but you're you're finding
against reality but
on the other side once we're all
enlightened it's just going to be
you know um
a co-creative construction and um
you know it shouldn't take a lot of
computational efforts to run something
like that
um it's a kind of like a lazy evaluated
uh you know computational construct so
thermodynamically
um this would this this kind of
computational fractal would appear as
something that's basically in
thermodynamic equilibrium all the time
because that's kind of what we want to
be i want to be in a thermodynamic
equilibrium with my environment pretty
much all the time so when i move around
you know the equilibrium shouldn't
really be disturbed much
why why should it right
cool
interesting so
there's a few different ways we could go
we'll definitely return to this
thermodynamic idea
but you mentioned again going back
looping to the beginning
you talked about the world as a
consequence of things existing
and definitely the fe p free energy
principle plays around with like what is
a thing
and what is a particular thing it's upon
particular being like specific but also
like a particle
and it turns out that the particles that
we care about aren't just the particles
that were in the ideal gas law not your
grandpa's thermodynamics but active
particles
that are cybernetic so they engage in
anti-dissipative
strategy
and those are the kinds of things that
we want to have a physics for
and so just like there's a info
thermodynamics for inert particles or we
can say even ones with constrained
affordances
we want to generalize that kind of
framework
so that also it applies to active
systems with agency and then just like
you can see maybe newtonian physics as a
special case or limit or an asymptote or
attractable approximation to certain
quantum systems
similarly inert systems are kind of like
the um
nested smaller systems of larger systems
with more agency but that's kind of the
idea or one of them with active that by
having a framework for particular things
as dynamic active entities
we can then collapse back to explain
passive entities but then also
maybe even figure something out about
how active entities work
i don't know as much about the buddhist
theology and that side but it's really
interesting to hear about it
uh yes definitely you know the in
buddhist
traditions like the um
one of the
kinds of training of the mind that you
you can do um the unexcelled yoga tantra
is a very sophisticated system of
visualizations and these visualizations
they
always
involve um some very kind of specific
images of you know countless buddhas and
bodhisattvas in all kinds of systems of
interconnected energy beaming um
uh
intricate mandalas and so on so forth so
there's a there's a whole um
pattern to it
and
it's their kind of imagistic way of
essentially
contemplating this kind of
structure of the universe is and seeing
in
this way as
you know the the the the
the next side of the nexus's next sign
um the the the points of uh you know
confluence of the universe that um
generate a lot of um
uh
behavior of the universe that you know
it's it's not quite random universe
isn't isn't random it's a it's a
you just you should really see it as
just simply a one big neural network
um that is computing something uh that
you know important to it
um
so
all these um entities they
they are being visualized in in these
traditions and the contemplations of
that allow you to really tune into um
those kind of energy flows so
uh like yeah this is it's it's how it's
how the universe is is generated by
you know the the mind of um you can say
the mind of god or the the fundamental
mind and then there are lots of smaller
active um
particles
in that mind that generate aspects of
the world and so on so forth and you
know finally you get to something like
um how the 3d space is generated out of
that and so on and so on so that it's
it's all described somewhere in the
buddhist canon
and they have extremely detailed
description of how
how reality is connected this way and
and it definitely can be understood in
terms of um uh what you just would you
just mentioned this kind of like you
know this active particle because
really if you think about what does it
what does it mean to for two
informational beings to meet right like
you're essentially a black hole uh to um
another computational process
because if if we are both touring
complete then we are black holes to each
other
we could just
you know run each other's computation
forever
um
so yeah like the
the the the the the the the the issue of
being a particle here is sort of
um
it is very it's very interesting it's
it's it's very deep because a particle
is sort of you know you can think about
it as it's it's a thing that kind of
has a perspective of a point but the but
but looks at the the world just
stretched all all around it right like
it interacts with like all the world
around it and you know black hole
the kind of information wraps around
around it um
is sort of something like being squashed
into a point so it's a very good model
for uh modeling all kinds of physical uh
physical systems and i think
um i think it would be also interesting
to implement something like this as a
you know computational model make this
sort of um
this sort of active particle a
distributed unit of computation in a
very lightweight actor system
um and just simply uh have a system that
will allow you to run
millions upon millions of these um
little active inference um
particles
and you know instead of trying to come
up with a generative model just create
something that
can assemble itself into a generative
model
having this sort of physics inspired
idea so i i think this is a really
powerful way of thinking about it
cool
interesting so i'm gonna loop back but
if anybody watching live wants to put a
question in the youtube live chat
or to um join this twitter space but
otherwise i'm just gonna loop back
again there's many places that uh we
could go
i guess
one angle that might be fun to explore
is
kind of like culture as our extended
cognitive niche
and the top-down priors that culture
provides and the scaffolds
that it allows for development within
and then
framing that as like a psycho social
technology especially as we're living
through like a technological change
so how do we think about
technology changes
and
the classic technologies and the bodily
technologies
metaverse just
what does technology have to do with our
path
um
i think it was marshall mcluhan who
you know said that uh or he wrote uh in
in the gutenberg galaxy that um
we are the sex organs of the machine
world
the
the way we're
we
the where we're headed i think uh well i
i'm quite confident that that's where
we're headed is uh
uh technological singularity right the
the convergence of ideas of um uh
technology with biology with um
full integration of all
aspects of human experience into in into
into one thing and i think this is the
kind of stuff that we're going to be
seeing um from now on in the world
um in terms of
you know the say um
you mentioned body technology the
neural link for example elon musk is
hoping they will be able to test neural
income people next year
uh neural link is gonna change the world
tremendously within
within months or or you know it's uh
it's it's it's
it's it's such a transformative piece of
technology once it's unleashed that it's
really difficult to imagine what world
is gonna be like once it's out there
it's because the brain simply
automatically
figures out how to
deal with any kind of signal so all you
have to do is to
you know
put a big multi-layer perceptron on the
other side of this
um signal and
with time you can train it to
send pump out any commands from your
brain to to a computer and that kind of
interfaces is just like a year and a
half
uh and a half maybe away or two years
away from being a commercially available
thing that you can just go and and get
and you know once something like this is
available it's a bi-directional
interface
so you will be able to simply um send
people a software update and
you know just give them all the
information that is necessary for them
to realize the nature of reality right
away
so
anybody who wants to be enlightened
could just go to a shop and say like
okay download the download the program
and boom um
you know that's that's something that
could be done
and the reason for that is simply that
um we don't really need to figure out
too much about how um
our neural networks work we just have to
um simulate similar conditions to create
a physical system system like that and
our neural networks let's automatically
extend into that environment um and you
know transition into
into um sort of a bit world or something
like that it's it's it's a it's it's
it's something that we can do
um you know existing in a metaverse and
liberating yourself from the confine of
a physical body i really recommend um
neil stephenson's uh fall or dog in hell
it's uh it's a beautiful account of what
uh what bit world is like and um there's
there's some bits of physics in there
that are just absolutely astounding it's
one of the most
uh you know best researched uh sci-fi
stories around around this kind of issue
so we're gonna be seeing a lot of this
kind of um
stuff showing up you know people are
building a lot of interesting technology
um for uh interacting with with
computers
that is
you know more and more geared
essentially towards being some sort of
form of mind control either through some
sort of brain sensing headsets or um
uh you know maybe some sort of sensors
on the wrist or or whatever but that
that kind of integration with the
machine is um is is kind of a natural
thing for us to do
it's it's always been like that i mean
that's the point of life we
we are a living thing right that is
holding on to a bunch of dead stuff
if if i knew how i would throw away my
bones and hold on to something made out
of metal but that's essentially what my
body is doing it's just holding on to
this
right like it's it's it's it's just a
bunch of dead tissue
and uh
you know our neural network is just
simply
adapting around it and evolving around
it so we will um
create technology that will extend our
senses into all kinds of you know
aspects of the electromagnetic spectrum
and so on so forth all of this stuff is
really coming and and transitioning to
you know all kinds of different modes of
experience is going to be something um
something really interesting and um
you can start
practicing
um you know all kinds of um
uh
arts of the mind today to prepare
yourself for this kind of thing
um
the game is on right once meta versus uh
uh is there someone someone has to be
telling a vitaly chernobyl or
one of those guys
all right awesome thanks so um just a
few notes so on the sensory substitution
david eagleman is a professor and has
given a lot of talks a lot of cool work
where there's like a vest with sensors
and all these other kind of wearables
that people do learn to integrate and
have these inter sensory experiences
kind of like synesthesia but it opens up
a whole nother level with the
biofeedback like it's one thing to have
a cultural tradition of observe your
heart rate
will it be a different thing when you're
going to be in an immersion studio and
the color and the frequency is going to
be related to your heart rate
variability things that might be
just beyond subtle
or impossible for a limited lifetime of
training to
provide you access to some of the entire
receptive cues and then how will that
influence our generative models so that
was one point about sensory substitution
biofeedback and the way that active
inference is a framework that's flexible
enough to deal with that so it's not
just restricted to the senses that we
have or the things that we're inferring
about today because our generative model
can change
and then i wanted to read
a quote from the recent paper that we're
discussing in active stream number 34.
so this is from axel constance paper the
free energy principle it's not about
what it takes it's about what took you
there
and this is gonna speak to potentially
about how there is this almost
i
wouldn't know whether it's truly
post-modern but sense that everyone is
right like you talked about how
everyone's behavioral approach is right
and different cultures are also
incomparable relative to each other yet
also you have preferences
if nothing else as realized by your
regime of attention
and we need to be making good decisions
like it's not just a preference where we
step if we want to continue living so
how do we square that circle with kind
of the need for a rigor and exactness
and
translation into computational systems
yet also this kind of radical inter
subjectivity so here's what axel
constant wrote
the rational constraint over the priors
is the fact that the approximate
subjective posterior cue or future prior
will not only be bayesian but also will
always be the best guess relative to
what the true posterior ought to be
in short under the free energy principle
even though priors refer to
psychological states of the system
updates of the system make those priors
in approximation of what they should
have been had the prior been updated
with exact base
thus it might be said that priors under
the free energy principle cut across the
objective subjective dichotomy they are
subjective while satisfying a rational
constraint mandated by the existence of
the system per se
so that's a way to
radically condition
on the existence of an active entity
and then what are the implications as
far as perception action conditioned on
that existence of an entity so
that's something that's
related to active and maybe it relates
to what you're thinking about too it
certainly does it's it's what i it's
what i mentioned before um that i like
to describe in terms of the
transcendental knowledge and the
transcendental experience
um the transcendental knowledge is you
know the the knowledge of how things are
the the the reason why we we we can have
such knowledge is that
simply um
you know the universe follows definite
laws that's that's a kind of a given if
if it didn't then we wouldn't be able
then
it wouldn't really be able to exist as a
um
as a stable structure
so having the transcendental knowledge
knowing how things are is is help of the
the equation based on
how things are
um the service based only how things are
what is the the construct that's behind
the fail of your perception
you can say like well you know this is
the this is what i perceive and and
these are the choices that i have and
these are these are the kind of
decisions the decisions that i i i make
but because i i have this transcendental
knowledge of what is really that what
what what what really are the hidden
causes uh the real real hidden causes
that that are not observable to me um
you know i can
uh
i can make this best guess as
as
as the code goes and and i sort of know
that this is in the right direction
i i simply know because there is one
correct way uh it's so so this best
guess is really it's just a gradient
right um it's uh it's
that's that's kind of what what my ever
adjusting best guess of where um
that movement in that space should be
um that that is the gradient uh in which
i have to go and as long as i'm making
small enough steps i will be able to say
that like well you know are the
observations uh
are my observations con um confirming
that my guesses are getting better or or
not and if if they are then i can just
simply follow that direction right
so
this active inference view um
is
is sort of
you have to also look look at this from
the sort of like a almost like a
perpendicular perspective what is it
like to be an active inference uh
agent uh and you know from from the from
the moment
in the moment of perception and this and
what these guesses really are is simply
you know this bayesian uh
characterization of the guess what it
really is is just a feeling
quite frankly
the agent has a feeling that this is the
right way to go
right that's that's what it manifests um
itself to to an agent
so it's right it is it is very much um
yeah it's a very related perspective
so let me
ask a question you talked about this
local
gradient descent or somehow gradient
inference
how do we know that following
the local gradient in terms of space and
time
how do we know that that's the right
way to go long-term or even a right or a
effective way and there's definitely a
few ways that we talk about this
inactive so i would love to hear what
you think like how do we make sure that
local gradient chasing doesn't
get us into a cold zack or a local
maxima
um
you know i i don't have a very um clear
answer to this but i have a um
i have an idea where to go in terms of
research
um for um
some solutions to this
one way would be to try to come up with
a system that um
uh
you know mathematically has uh
has a sort of desirable property
but another way to go is to simply
construct a system that has a certain
kind of random randomness in sampling
the environment because that seems to be
the key um that what the fundamental
algorithms of uh you know the brain um
uh are like i know if you guys are
familiar with uh jeff hawkins of numenta
and his
thousand brains uh theory and
his uh hierarchical temporal memory and
work on
sparse distributed representations
um
they're working on on computational
models of neurons that are very
biologically uh
so
they they take the basis for their
computational modeling to be a cortical
column and they have some interesting uh
computational models of of that
and it seems to be the case that
you know in terms of hardware
implementation what nature seems to be
doing to ensure this
sort of robustness and not being stuck
is simply um you know you take you take
a signal and you project it onto
some collection of cortical columns that
are going to be modeling that signal so
it could be a part of your
occipital cortex
and then
that signal is distributed among those
those columns in such a way that each
gets a sap sample of the signal so if
this was like an image then maybe you
know
um
you you blank out um
20 30 percent of the pixels uh for each
different different set for each of the
columns so they have a they have a
different perception
um so you have this random projection
and each each column then has you know
um
it's kind of like a random you can think
about differently it's it's a kind of a
random basis um
against which we're doing uh essentially
a
principal component analysis later
um
so
once you have enough of them and you and
you get an average that's how the system
becomes robust and it's able to always
detect the um
uh
the
you know direction
of the greatest benefit and it's not
just um
you can't quite easily to be stuck
locally because in some of your bases um
in in some of these uh you know by the
virtue of just choosing the bases
randomly um in some of these you're
gonna find
um
uh you're gonna you're gonna pick out
elements of the signal that are not
local
and and these columns were simply by the
virtue of their you know the
disposition their their initial wiring
um
become the the
antennas for the frequencies in the
signal um that are simply non-local
so
that's the
um that's what i'm thinking
we can simply build and stop worrying
about um being stuck in
um
uh in local uh local optimums uh
although you know i i don't have a
mathematic
type mathematical theory behind
to show that it will work but i have a
feeling it will so it might be a
research direction
thanks
i'd like to actually share a few more
technical ways that we can address this
i think it's just interesting to
contrast with the answer that you
provided so i'm going to give four
examples and i hope that there's more as
well
so the first way that we can escape this
kind of local gradient chasing is
evolution and ecology and embodied
hardware and wet wear so like the ant
leg doesn't have to do an all by all
control theory question
it's an evolved entity so we know the
parameters have worked in probably
similar ecologies and then the physical
embodiment of the system restricts the
solutions so that the things that it is
trying to solve are the right things to
solve so that's kind of a big general
first catch-all point which is for
physical embodied systems
it just kind of works because it has to
otherwise it wouldn't be there like
you're not going to see birds who have a
maladaptive flight model
and so those cases that we're going to
talk about now are like kind of
computational edge cases when we want to
do something that isn't within the scope
of a soft bodied organism so this is
like big data fitting so the second
approach which is the first of the big
data is variational bayesian methods
and other statistical methods so
variational bayesian methods you can
learn about it in other
streams
but basically they fit the parameters on
a really constrained family of
distributions so that the optimization
of that family is basically
straightforward it's kind of like making
a map of a map we talk about it in
active stream number 32 and a few other
places like 26
but you can set up the problem so that
the optimization is straightforward just
like a linear regression with the least
squares l2 norm it's possible to set up
more complicated variational bayesian
models that have similar optimization
properties
the next is the third which is the
helmholtz decomposition and so the
helmholtz decomposition takes a vector
field and it decomposes
into a irrotational so kind of like
straight up and down that's like putting
a ruler on the mountain just finding it
where it's the most pointed up
so there's the irritational component
and then there's the solenoidal or like
the just curling around component and
that's kind of the isocontour like a
hiking map
and so
you can put the gas on going downhill or
uphill depending which way you want to
go
and then
also rotate on an iso contour to
sometimes help escape local maxima
because it's kind of like hiking like
that's how you escape a local maxima
hiking by combining going straight up
the hill or down the hill with also
navigating with the curls
and then the last category which is
really broad is computational heuristics
so that includes like structure learning
as well as tree rollouts and stochastic
search and just all the ways that it's
possible to
even if you don't have a guarantee that
you found the best solution
you may be able to find one that keeps
your job or that feeds everyone on earth
or does something else so it might be
possible to use all the kinds of
computational heuristics that people use
every day that don't even have to be
active related
we can make computers work and so we
don't need to solve this to like the
most extreme
um
devilish
case
sometimes it's just enough to do it on
real data and so
hopefully that's a useful way to think
about
ways to escape local maxima does that
relate to anything that you see as
relevant
uh i mean yes uh this is this is all
about um
uh you know the the
these things are basically all about the
fact that
ultimately you can't hide the signal
anywhere
right the the the universe has this
holographic nature it's a it's an image
of itself within itself
it's it's probably the most one of the
most um
the nice one of the nicest uh visual
analogies that i heard uh
this expressed as was this zen concept
of gigi muga the total
interconnectedness of all things you can
sort of imagine like a multi-dimensional
spider web with drops of dew suspended
in it and each of the drops of dew
contains a reflection of all the other
drops of you and all the drops of view
within the reflections of reflections
and so on so forth
so you know that's that's kind of what
the universe is and that's why you
always have the global signal
it's always there
the the you you will always be able to
know what is the path of least
resistance towards nirvana
that that is by design but to to to know
um to be able to feel it you have to
have the transcendental knowledge
so uh in in this case like what you said
the structure models right like coming
up with the uh
understanding the structure of the space
that you're operating in allows you to
keep a global context
um
despite you know um your your local uh
uh
local circumstances so the the ideal
active inference agent is simply
something that just automatically builds
a map of its environment as it goes goes
along
and
if if it's paying enough attention to
all the inputs that it's getting from um
from its environment then you know the
the the full nature of the environment
it's always possible to reconstruct it
with a sufficiently complex um
model uh internal model of the world so
that you you actually understand what
you experience
i mean there might be some sort of
critical limit you know
the critical minimum from sort of
perspective of
the book this canon i suppose um is
you know being a human we we are sort of
best positioned in the buddhist canon to
become enlightened better than the gods
and uh you know better than demons and
so on so forth because our life has just
about enough suffering in it
that it pushes us in a certain direction
but it's not easy enough that we never
really contemplate you know um our our
suffering that kind of thing so there is
like a computational minimum but once
once that minimum is pre it is passed
right um a conscious agent will simply
be able to interpret the signal and i
think we should be able to build an
algorithm that's going to be completely
universal across um you know
all implementation and that's some
that's going to be something that's
mostly based on hashing so a very von
neumann architecture um
maybe like a combinatory logic compiled
expression to to to a graph machine and
then you can essentially compute you
know gigantic non-regressive
active inference neural network that
just never really forgets anything
and it automatically redistributes all
its its knowledge about the world across
itself without any effort whatsoever to
to to program that in any special way
that's the in my opinion the holy grail
of active inference research we we we
will be able to to come up with this
algorithm
eventually
well if you expect and prefer it then
let's do it so i wanted to
read um a little short quote this is
from a english translation of a story by
zhuangzi
apologies on the pronunciation who is a
early taoist writer and so this is a
butcher
a meat cleaver person describing
their skill set
so here's the translation in english
what i care about is the way which goes
beyond skill when i first began cutting
up oxen all i could see was the ox
itself
after three years i no longer saw the
whole ax or ox and now
now i go by spirit and don't look with
my eyes perception and understanding
have come to a stop and the spirit moves
where it wants i go with the natural
makeup strike in the big hollows guide
the knife through the big openings and
follow things as they are so i never
touch the small ligaments or tendons
much less a main joint a good cook
changes his knife once a year because he
cuts
a mediocre cook changes his knife once a
month because he hacks
i've had this knife for 19 years and
i've cut up thousands of oxen with it
and yet the blade is as good as though
it had just come from the grindstone
there are spaces between the joints and
the blade of the knife really has no
thickness if you insert what has no
thickness into such spaces then there's
plenty of room more than enough for the
blade to play that's why after 19 years
the blade of my life is still as good as
when it first came from the grindstone
[Laughter]
wonderful
yeah pretty cool story about in active
inference what we might call
skilled performance
it's also an example of like in cultured
and extended cognition
and about how the generative model
changed as the master increased
incompetency their internal generative
model changed they saw something
different they didn't see the same auxin
that they saw when they were younger and
then that changed how they physically
acted
and then they used their own
proprioceptive feedback to guide that
flow and then there's almost a cultural
layer around it
if the story is read
fully
with like somebody who has a higher
station in life also kind of paying that
respect
so it's a very cool story yes
yes definitely
um you know the
the
the sort of
consequence of of this is also that you
know think about your body as the knife
if you really
have a proper model and uh minimize free
energy correctly you should not be
growing older or die
it's a result of the loss of information
and it's possible to grow younger and
it's uh
uh you know you can stay young
indefinitely
it's just a matter of having a
sufficiently open state of mind to
minimize
all the free energy uh which is
essentially damage that accumulates as a
result of you know
just wear and tear and if it's something
that you don't attend to consciously in
order to heal your body then over many
years of life
damage accumulates accumulates and you
eventually die and it's completely
unnecessary
it literally is just a bad habit
i'll provide just a counter point and uh
note that it's an open theological
question so this is a quotation from
the same actual constant 2021 paper
so from the point of view of the free
energy principle
when considering morphic organisms like
insects that go undergo metamorphosis
like an ant
it may be said that it is the life cycle
that corresponds to the thing whose
integrity is maintained over
evolutionary time
not the specific form that the system
takes at one stage of its development eg
the adult form of a frog this casts the
fep within the realm of process ontology
versus substance ontology so one take is
like the perfect active agent is gonna
do phagocytosis and cellular
regeneration and it will be like in this
sort of non-equilibrium steady states
where it won't change and it'll look
just like it did at the time when it
started doing that and another take is
actually like
the life cycle of the ant or the life
cycle of the colony will be
recapitulated with fidelity and also
variation potentially
but
within the cycle there may be even a
constant flux and a constant aging like
every ant is trudging towards
dissolution but the colony can
recapitulate itself so i think it's a
question at which level
or which levels
we will see that kind of
regeneration happening or not
i mean you know ultimately uh this is a
this is one another way to sort of
approach the subject of um
nondual awareness and and the mind-body
duality
is that
um
these both both of these extremes they
really
are uh
two views on the same thing
you
can sort of dissolve yourself as an
individual and become just just the
process
and you don't you know in your
consciousness simply is the
consciousness of that process
or you can become an individuated thing
and have an individual experience
the enlightened mind can exist at all
these
levels of organization
simultaneously so any manifestation that
you want to have in the world
is is just a manifestation of the mind
it's kind of like ghost in the shell um
downloading yourself into a different
body except you can be multiple bodies
at the same time as your consciousness
grows
um you know you can just use more
actuators that's that's that's all there
is to it and then um you
you can become a thing that has uh er
that has you know a sort of a group
identity of some sort so it's i think
it's just it's a spectrum right and it's
it's simply a choice for you as an
individual that if you want
um and if you would like your body to
persist indefinitely you should be able
to uh get there um there is nothing that
prevents an active inference agent to to
achieve something like this and you know
i'm speaking of my own personal
experience is that a few years ago um
i started realizing that my health
wasn't exactly
um in
great shape and started doing something
about it and you know done some
biological tests for my biological age
versus chronological age and the the
results are coming you know who are
quite interesting like the
uh
what is the uh
uh insight tracker a very interesting
plot
and dna based uh
test that measures all kinds of
biomarkers estimated my chronological
age at 30 versus uh
sir biological age at 30 versus
chronological 35 and another test based
on the methylation patterns of the dna
estimated by age at 33 versus 35
and you know i'm pretty sure that in a
couple of years i'm gonna i'm going to
push it down to 20. repairing um
damage of the cellular level with
compounds like nads and search and other
surgeons
um you know there's there's a lot of
really interesting longevity stuff
coming up these days anybody who's about
40 you know under 40 years old can has a
very reasonable expectation of about 140
years of life with the technology that
we have today and technology is
improving exponentially right mrna gives
us essentially a software update
mechanism we can make ourselves produce
anything we want
um so the matter of
repairing your body at the genetic level
um with with some sort of mrna vaccine
and in a personalized medicine session
it's going to be something like
you know a reality within a decade so um
yeah like the but but but ultimately
that's that all that stuff is not even
really necessary if you can tune into
the signal that you get from your body
and learn to um just feel when your body
is resting and healing
um
it will persist indefinitely i'm quite
sure i'll get there eventually
very
interesting thanks for sharing it
welcome blue and retool if you'd like to
speak you can request or anyone can
write a question in the chat
yeah this has been pretty fun and let's
keep talking i think there's a few more
topics we could
explore
so i'm looking back to the chat so one
comment and again blue retool or anyone
else please feel free to ask a question
so
you talked about kind of being a black
hole or like a black box to another
informational process
and i think that insight is also
something that's been
stated in different ways by different
knowledge systems so daniel dennett
would call that kind of like the
intentional stance
and that's the origins of the whole
philosophical zombie thought question
it's the basis of the turing test
john cyril's um basically like chinese
room i think is what it was originally
called the idea of passing messages to
somebody who's inside of a room using a
lookup table
and um it's also central to the framing
of actimp where there can be
a shared generative model in a
communicating dyad
but
because of the structure of the
partition of the entity the particular
entity and its niche which can be a
social niche
you don't get to peer behind the veil
it's just external states generative
processes passing sensory stimuli to the
particular entities generative model and
it's like if it were anything other than
that then it would be different
if it were something that you were
getting direct insight to then that
would be inside of your particular
entity and it wouldn't be an external
state be like an internal state
and so it's just kind of a
cool way that the actin
topology of action
allows us to look at a lot of these more
qualitative examples and thoughts around
like well what if we are like black
boxes to each other or maybe even
there's something else happening with
information like a black hole maybe you
could give more info on that but then
also we can build this
to model the kinds of systems that we
want to
know about the actual information
boundaries of like online teams
yeah so that's the the
the the most difficult problem uh in in
the universe right is to is to create
this translation between two minds
is that we are um
just this compute this computational
block holds to each other
but at the same time you know we we can
generate some sort of negative entropy
for others right um
so
that's
essentially you know everything that
neural networks do
is uh communication through some sort of
language right so um
what what the world what the world is
um to us is some sort of story that we
have to tell ourselves that um describes
the name the nature of it so we invent
categories and assign um assign meanings
to concepts and images and so on so
forth and we tell ourselves like this is
what this is what the structure of our
environment is and so on so forth and
then eventually we come up with um
descriptions of reality that we can both
uh agree upon you know we we just
develop language to to talk about things
that um you know are quote unquote
objectively true as in uh can be
perceived by
more than one person right and that's
how we and that's how we that's how we
start piercing this veil and
understanding that process like how this
veil is constructed what is the purpose
of language well what the word how how
language really
um
how language really arises as
as a tool of communication for
explaining the nature of the world and
um
learning to listen to
someone's subjective experience and
taking it as as literal just simply
assuming that you know whatever whatever
someone is saying what their experience
is just you know assume
what they're saying it is what they're
experiencing
and ask yourself like you know how can
this possibly be true that is the way of
actually
piercing that veil that's uh
figuring out the internal model right
the the hidden causes because if you
can't see you can't see the hidden
causes being behind the the sensory
input that you're
that you're receiving but you can
speculate
you know what what what might they be
and that act of speculation the updating
of your internal model based on that uh
coming up with these new new ideas and
again you you again have this looped
into into generative thinking
so you speculate about the hidden causes
and say like well you know okay this is
the experience i'm i'm
i'm
i have described by this by this entity
it tells me that this is what it's
experiencing this is what i what i
assume might be causing all of this and
you know once you once you run through
enough iterations of this um
of the cycle you can actually arrive at
perfect understanding that you and this
other entity um
have the same understanding of the world
and that
is essentially you know
um if there are fans of you know ghost
in the shell
online this is the deal that project
2501 offers to
motoku
uh to to become one entity because this
this moment of full rocking that you are
basically two ends of the same entity uh
that is that the the solution of the
of the um of the self the the solution
of the marker blanket and essentially
you know
um and an integration into a a being of
a higher consciousness
so
that is essentially the name of the game
right to
to to do this to to to come up with a
description language um
using words that are familiar to a
person based on their culture
uh and their understanding of the world
and the the priors that they received
from from from from the culture of how
to interpret uh the signs that they
perceive and so on so forth to to
understand this is kind of a cipher um
all of that is a kind of a cipher into
the mind and once you have a perfect
understanding of that you can come up
with words that simply will
guide someone towards the transcendental
experience that's necessary towards
enlightenment
so
that's that's that's how these two
things uh relate here
thank you
speaker blue
um can you hear me am i good yeah yeah
yep
so
how do you know that we're not already
part of some larger picture like where
we're all
like rocking and fulfilling our
essential roles in
the part of
something larger than ourselves
i mean we are that's that that's exactly
what's going on um it's a
it's a matter of
you know um
a great description of like how how to
approach this uh this topic is the
alchemist by paulo carlo uh he literally
lays out
you know
a way of being
that that allows you to take advantage
of the fact that the world is
constructed this way there are portals
to adventures to
strange realms to
time travel to all kinds of crazy things
and you just simply have to know um how
to find them and it's a matter of
adjusting your perception
and
noticing that the reality around you is
not what it seems to be it's very very
psychedelic
and
you know um for instance my life
experience because i spent um
i spent a lot of time in japan i've been
living there for
um 10 years now and you know um
that is my home my life is very much
like a murakami story um
very strange very psychedelic weird
occurrences
you know people and
um
topics of conversation
and and and and and kind of things that
show up and characters that are just
really improbable um it's
it's it's right there
but we are so busy
with you know the um what becomes our
day-to-day experience that we are
essentially hypnotized into um
a sub-optimal way of living instead of
enjoying the creations of the mind we
are being bogged down by them you know
some dude comes along and says like hey
you have to pay the income tax
you work for me
and that's how and that's how it gets
you it ties you to the
um to a wrong dream right and the
buddhist term for that is the samsara
that shared the dream that uh that we're
into
but the the thing about the dream and
and liberating yourself of the dream is
that liberating yourself from the dream
the the experience of nirvana is to
experience the consciousness of the
universe as the universe
you know
as a full thing
how it is you that is generating this
reality for yourself and everybody
within it and that experience is um
automatically
you know
tran transforms your
um
your way of seeing the world because
it's a it's a it's a complete expression
of joy um
uh garland sutra talks about this uh
what it's like to be an enlightened
being who experiences the world like
that
um everything that's happening in the
world
to us may seem like you know a challenge
or um
uh
source of suffering and so on so forth
but in in a way
it's a it's an opportunity for us to
become um to get on the right path the
world is always giving you the uh
opportunity to to get on the right path
and
and keep walking
and you know sometimes that has to be
for suffering if you stray too far
that's that's how you get into
um into the right direction and learning
how to just recognize the omens and um
uh you know taking part in your own in
the adventure that is
is already there for you um kind of your
your future self laid it out for
yourself for you know
for yourself
um you as a fully enlightened being that
you already are your your consciousness
just simply needs to catch up to it so
yes it's it's it's exactly is exactly
how things are and uh you know buddhist
techniques or simply
tools for the mind to learn how to
put that in action in day to day
experience and just make it a reality
thank you for that awesome answer so
when you talk about
like everything that you
have done to this point leads to the
next point and you need to
like just follow through
do you really believe that there's
something
like equivalent to free will
or are we just the product of our last
time step
you you know the way i joke about it is
that you're
you
you have free will and so far as you are
free to suffer if you want to
um
if you know the path of dharma is that
there is only one way to live
but within that one way there is an
infinite potentiality for expressing
yourself creatively in any way um
you want
so as long as you stick to the rules of
you know the universal path you get
um
an an infinite opportunity for
self-expression out of it
so
free will is just um
it's a wrong way to think about it
it's a it's a it's a it's a concept that
um
you know it's
okay i i have a great analogy uh citizen
of the galaxy
uh by robert uh heinlein a fun
fantastic um
sci-fi story there is a
uh there's a boy there who um you know
uh
is being sold as a as a slave and um
bought by this the this who
eventually um frees him from from his
slavery and uh smuggles him out of the
uh the planet as a free trader and the
free traders are you know priding
themselves to be the freest people in
the galaxy they can go wherever they
want they can trade with whoever they
want they they live on their ships in a
very sort of matriarchal um very tight
family uh
uh
kind of arrangements and you know they
they're they're free to roam the galaxy
except there's basically zero individual
freedom on the ship because your
position in that complex society is
dictated not only by very precise family
relationship that you have with every
single member of the crew because it's
all family but also your function um
um uh you know
as a person on the ship so that's like a
second layer
uh your job and the third is just the
general social standing and and
seniority so they're the most
constrained people as individuals and
yet they just you know they don't choose
what they eat because it's being cooked
for them it just happens to be extremely
lavish and tasty and comes from all
kinds of worlds they don't choose where
to go because the captain chooses it
just happens to be the most interesting
places in the
in the universe and so on so forth right
so none of them has any individual
freedom but they're extremely free as
people
and i think this is uh the best uh
description of what uh
a real realization of free will uh
looks like you know it should look like
in a society i i
really recommend that book
so i'm going to share a quote from the
alchemist and then a few lines of willy
blake because they're relevant for our
active journey so here is two lines from
the alchemist
there's only one way to learn the
alchemist answered it's through action
everything you need to know you have
learned through your journey you don't
even have to understand the desert all
you have to do is contemplate a simple
grain of sand and you will see in it all
the marvels of creation
so that's from the alchemist by paulo
coghill
and then here's um the first four lines
of the poem auguries of innocence by
william blake
to see a world in a grain of sand and
heaven in a wild flower hold infinity in
the palm of your hand and eternity in an
hour
so similar
grain of sand contemplating
and
um
just a few
relevant pieces of
art that are
also part of our
conversation so thanks for letting me
share them because
there's a technical side to what we're
discussing
with active and also with the computer
stuff
but
it's also
very deeply experiential so yes that is
my question to then send back to the
group which is how will we think about
our
like on body experience
as
we start to change our technology more
and more
like
is that preferable to be in that setting
that you just laid out kristoff where
there's like
at one level you're very constrained but
then at a different level you have
a lot of degrees of freedom
like again how do we
make the decisions now that are the
right across all those possibilities
well i think it's a matter of preference
and you know i can't change i can't wait
to change my body plan for uh for an
octopus um that is such a wonderful way
to be uh everything i know about
cephalopods suggests that it's going to
be a really interesting way to
experience the world so
um imagine that that's just what would
you get like whatever body plan you want
whatever experience of the world you
want you you can get it
um
and uh there's there's no reason why uh
you know this is something that you can
experience in the mind alone right um
the tradition of lucid dreaming for
instance
um
allows you to
uh this is also something that's uh you
know perfected by uh tibetan buddhists
by by the way they have a very
interesting yogas of dream and sleep and
the whole point of these things is to
essentially be conscious and aware uh
through all the possible
um states uh of the of the mind so that
you can practice dharma 24 7.
um so that that's the kind of thing that
allows you to experience this a little
bit um i i don't really have dreams at
all uh strangely but um i don't have
this ability to visualize in my mind
this way that's something i'm working on
but uh people who do you know um they
usually
model some sort of experience in the
world but the next level of that is to
just model your body experience as a
different thing it's very difficult to
imagine what it must feel like to be a
different um
different creature but it's certainly
possible and something that um that we
can learn how to do eventually
virtual reality also provides an
interesting uh possibility of you know
unplugging yourself from your usual body
plan
there was an art installation
a couple years ago um
some sort of like a you know a device
that makes you essentially experience
flying like a bird you can flop your
wings and so on so forth so you get
strapped onto a device put in the vr
headset and so on and a certain kind of
dissolution of
what it means to be you can happen for
for this technology and i think this is
going to get more and more immersive and
it's going to get really really fun and
you will be able to
really suspend your um
uh your your
belief in being uh you know uh one kind
of being and and just experience the
world or something something else
entirely again for something like neural
link
if you can
if you can pack that kind of experience
into the into that data pipe then we
might be able to see
uh
you know what i would predict out of um
out of the sort of brain computer
interfaces is that you're going to have
two kinds of technologies showing up one
is going to be sort of like a consumer
electronics type you get some sort of
brain computer interface and it's useful
and you can do some basic things
but there's going to be some people like
me who are going to take it to the next
level like okay now i have this data
pipe what is the limit of what i can
what i can pack across that kind of um
that kind of uh barrier
um sorry the kind of data data path and
it turns out that it's a lot right
neural compression um
will allow you to basically transmit
entire concepts
to the mind directly so you should be
able to basically
have
a stream of you know something that the
brain can interpret as completely
immersive virtual environments of of
your own design
being beamed into your head for
something like a neural link
um with whatever experience of anything
that you want a little bit
um
it's gonna get wild
so i have to say a couple of things here
can i jump in daniel okay
yes please
well i saw that dalai lama speak at the
neuroscience conference in 2005
probably
um and it was a really jarring
experience for me like i've been
buddhist probably since 1999
and seeing this
seeing him speak there like
really made me reevaluate my my thoughts
but he said like if we could find a pill
that could make us
perpetually happy we should all take it
um and what you're describing here with
the neurolink and like the data download
and pushing it to like the most extreme
limit like i would totally be there in
that boat with you like let me just see
what's possible
um but but also to the the comment that
you made about um
like the yoga of sleeping
it's uh like i one time did a 30 day
like 14 hours a day mantra recitation
practice
um and the entire it was a retreat right
so like i didn't do tv like i limited my
phone calls email like all i limited all
non-dharma activities and essentially
like i would and i don't dream also like
so i have to like throw in this comment
because like i i get like five dreams a
year
that i like wake up and like oh i had a
dream last night like it's like
surprising it's always insightful
but but i also like regularly i'm not
like oh i had the most amazing dream
last night like that doesn't happen to
me like i don't get like
cl and like people say wake up and just
journal them like i've tried all the
things
um
but but when i did the retreat i would
wake up in the middle of the night to
like use the restroom and i'd be like
reciting the mantra
all the time like i would wake up
reciting the mantra i'd go to sleep
reciting the mantra i would be on the
bathroom like on the toilet in the
middle of the night reciting the mantra
i'd be making breakfast reciting the
mantra it never stopped there was this
like grand purification of
my
mind that took place like during that
time
so i just wanted to share that um for
what it's worth
that's an awesome experience
yeah these mountains are super powerful
you know like the tibetans they they
they recite these things all the time
like omani
and so on so forth it's like um i find
it really powerful to
get into that state of mind because
ultimately you know ultimately you are a
recurrent neural network
that's that is what's what's going on
here we are recurring neural networks
that's how we generate our experience
and the more control we have we get over
this recurrence um
the better and mantras you know the
mantra is something that's supposed to
reinforce the mind
is it's kind of a way of providing a
clock you know it's just the same kind
of thing like um
that we do with um
uh
what is called uh
blending the input of with sines and
cosines uh for transformer in
transformer architectures uh positional
encoding yes uh sorry positional
encoding and mantra is a kind of uh
way of
obtaining a positional encoding uh just
having something repeating in the mind
so that you know you can
you can um
you can attach your consciousness to
experience better to experience in the
moment this is one of the um one of the
goals of these contemplative practices
of meditation is to simply
you know become conscious of the mark of
blanket and stay with that consciousness
and then we fall uh we we think we are
uh conscious of the moment but that's
just simply not true right like we are
always a little bit behind reality at
least five milliseconds or so from
perceptual perspective
um
and
being in that moment uh is is the name
of the game like practicing that that's
that feeling what what it feels to
actually minimize the free energy
instead of just being
spinning in the in the sort of the image
of the world that we have in our head
that we we perceive as reality
i practice this kind of thing
so there's definitely
active work about temporal thickness
like how the recent past and the recent
future
are
mapped or how they're
influencing the action selection in the
moment of an active agent
what are some
things that we can practice or things
that we would
i don't know how would we track that in
ourself
so you know the the
you have to sort of synchronize your
perception with um
some sort of clock so the the classic
way of uh doing that is either
minding your heart rate or
uh observing your breathing
or just generally having any kind of uh
you know biofeedback that could be used
or it could be a metronome um
you know uh
or any kind of tapping device
uh if you could configure something like
an apple watch to be
you know vibrating uh periodically that
would also be really useful
and
what
what we need to learn um
in order to operate our minds
effectively is to essentially
know the difference between the
experience in the moment as it's
happening and the memory of the
experience
an interesting
topic related to all of this is the
concept of chronic pain
um
you know pain um is sometimes defined as
as an emotion and
the question is like if something hurts
are you experiencing pain because there
is an actual physiological symptom that
needs to be addressed or is it
effectively a memory of um
a signal that is being triggered
um as a result of the fact that you
experience pain for long enough that it
had that its expression has become
essentially part of your neural
architecture
so
um a lot of people who are experiencing
chronic pain are really experiencing
effectively a memory of pain and there
is nothing really wrong with them
um and again speaking of experience here
i had i had some issues with chronic
pain for uh for a couple of years and
you know like every ct scan mri and any
other assessment of the
uh
affected area there was a hip cartilage
damage um uh that healed but pain
remained and there was like nothing
wrong with the sight and yet the pain
remained so
you know that's the
um
the the notion of this you know this the
sort of temporal thickness of this uh
how the how the perception has
updates um
uh has to update the internal model it's
a it's a very interesting problem
because it can go wrong and when your um
reception and interception are out of
whack and that could be as a result of
being autistic for instance um i think
that's a good uh autism is that kind of
it is that kind of problem it's a it's a
problem of you know um two strong um or
two week priors essentially
um
when whenever something like this
happens it becomes very difficult to
actually um get out of that kind of
state of mind but it it it is a state of
mind
and
by practicing this awareness in the
moment the being on the um
on the edge of the the market blanket
we
we can really learn how to distinguish
between these you know false signals
that are just generated by the mind and
the actual signal from the body
and
for me for instance learning these
skills
um was a path to learning how to heal my
body uh the kind of issues that i
managed to pull myself out of
were were quite interesting you know
like i had some it turned out that i had
essentially a neuromuscular congenital
issue uh in my left
uh on the left side of my neck that was
messing me up you know throughout uh the
radiating throughout from my body
creating this kind of like a weird twist
to the point where this actually shows
up on my mri as a yak of 11 torque so my
left occipital cortex is significantly
larger than than
my right hospital cortex it's kind of
it's it's a very interesting problem and
you know and and i became aware of this
this fact and um
after contemplating the free energy
principle i realized that my perception
of the world as as i see it is wrong for
where my body really should be you know
when i think i'm straight when they
think my posture is okay when they think
all kinds of other things that simply
isn't true as a result of me having
wrong perceptions as a result of
essentially a nerve
some sort of nerve impingement in my
neck
and that was a result of c-section
so i was kind of born with ptsd and free
energy principle like literally freed me
from all of that and my body is healing
as we speak like for the last during the
last year um my posture has improved
tremendously but it was all about
understanding like what is it i'm
supposed to be experiencing how does my
body know that i'm supposed to be level
and then just meditating on that and you
know
feeling how how the brain adjusts and
the um
and the body responds automatically it's
not something that i learned how to
straighten up to a good posture i sort
of learned how to let go
and let my
subconscious do the job
and it was all as a result of active
inference so there's a there's
tremendous amount of um power there um
to to help people with all kinds of
problems you know by um
explaining that
the nature of the experience
um and i i'm
this story doesn't even scratch the
surface of like you know the the kind of
experiences they had in this sort of
area
i think this is a great
moment for just our final
thoughts and comments
this is a really awesome discussion
though and i hope it's not our last one
so
blue if you would like to have any final
comments
hey oh sorry
for my little children
and only thank you and i hope we get to
have more discussion and comments
uh thank you for having me that was um
you know really enjoyable thanks for um
listening to my perspective i appreciate
it
yeah
definitely our honor and pleasure to do
so
not
traditional
active lab activities but
really
fun
and so
thanks again
to those listening
good luck we hope you participate with
active lab or
life or whatever it is
but you're probably already doing that
so
thanks kristoff in blue peace out you
too thank you
you